uh so let's uh let's uh start the
lecture uh can you uh so if you T if you
want to begin recording you
can okay okay so this lecture is on
visual
navigation now uh wait a minute
do so this this is the problem you have
a robot with a first person
camera and and then I I drop it into a
novel environment so initially we did
all these a lot of these experiments
were done in Cory Hall but after a while
I thought okay you want it to be truly
novel and there'll be ways in which
people can can cheat because they might
have thought of this environment so the
the all the subsequent experiments we
did we did them by renting airbnbs so
the rule is you rent an Airbnb you open
the door you put down your robot and
then you give the robot some task so my
theory is that that way we can claim we
are we have not cheated I mean it's a
novel
environment okay then the robot walks
around and then uh and then it's given
some goal so there is a there are a
variety of ways in which to specify
goals so uh one way to specify a goal is
uh is uh geometric right you say go 300
ft North 400 ft
East right this is rarely the goals that
you actually care about in practice in
practice what you care about is oh I'm
looking for the toilet or I'm looking
for a chair or I'm looking for a knife
or I want to know where is the kitchen
so these are what we call semantic goals
and uh that's that that's what I regard
as what a practical use of navigation
systems is right okay now what is the
classical solution to this problem so
the classical solution which comes from
the computer vision Community is called
structure
promotion the same solution in the uh
robotics Community is called slam but
it's exactly the same thing slam is just
a renaming of structure from
structure promotion is a term from
1980 uh slam is a term from 2000 so uh
okay uh the idea is that if you have
multiple images then what you do is you
reconstruct the 3D environment
okay so the 3D environment is uh
reconstructed here and there are a
number of papers that have been written
over the years on how to do this 3D
reconstruction and uh there are still
new papers being written and uh then
latest technology so the old techniques
are all based on finding corresponding
points and then doing triangulation so
that's the way you recover the 3D
geometry of the environment the latest
techniques involve using learning where
you train on some images and eventually
what you do is you are given a set of
images you recover the cameras and then
you recover the point cloud of the scene
so duster and mustard are examples of
that doesn't matter whichever way you do
it the goal here is 3D
deconstruction once you've done 3D
reconstruction then you solve a
different problem which is called the
path planning problem which is
essentially a purely computational
geometry exercise you the environment is
known the obstacles are known and you
have to find a connected path between a
start and a go so this uh you can see
how this will work for
geometric uh goals it's not necessarily
super smart for uh for uh semantic goals
what does this approach suggest for
semantic goals basically you just keep
searching until you find it right it
seems kind of slightly stupid
right okay uh the other remark here is
do we really need to uh so the classical
approach both does too little and does
too much so in what way does it do too
much it does this Recon so in the
classical slam solution you first
completely reconstruct the
environment okay do I need to
reconstruct the environment if all I
want to do is to go out of the door no
so it does too much okay it also does
too
little why why why does it do too little
because it hasn't got this semantic
context it hasn't uh so my favorite
example for this is uh you go to some
restaurant this the first time you've
gone to that restaurant and then you
need to go to the
restroom we somehow manage to know which
way to go right you do not have a map of
this restaurant because this is the
first time you've been in the restaurant
and yet you sort of have an intuition of
okay this is more promising and maybe
you'll ask a waer but very often you
just manage to find the way why because
you have a familiarity with places like
restaurants and and so on okay the same
is true in a home you go to a friend's
home you don't uh what's the the slam
Story the slam story will say you I mean
okay let's say I want to keep keeping
with this example of I would need to go
to the bathroom the solution would say
first I explore my friend's house
repeatedly taking lots and lots of views
then I built the complete map then I'm
going to find the way to the bathroom do
we do that no does this make sense no
okay uh so geometric 3D reconstruction
the world is insufficient because uh it
doesn't capture the semantic information
it cannot exploit patterns in the
layouts of spaces so all these spaces we
have some sense of where cubicles are
where corridors are and that's
essentially statistical in nature so uh
what's the technology for capturing that
machine learning so you have to find
some machine learning way of capturing
what are more plausible uh locations
plausible more fruitful paths and so
on
okay uh okay so let's see so so what has
happened is let me let me see if I can
move this guy out
somewhere okay uh so so uh somewhere
around
2016 2017 is when you know machine
learning techniques became popular in
computer vision and Robotics so there
was a form formulation of this problem
which was you either using reinforcement
learning or or imitation learning so the
idea there is and it would be goal
conditioned right so you specify a goal
and the goal could be a semantic goal
like chair or it could be a goal like uh
300 M North 200 M West and uh always the
objective is to get to the goal without
colliding with obstacles right that's
our framework
so uh so people uh started to use uh uh
machine learning techniques and there
are uh two obvious ways of doing this so
let's just think that through so how
would you do it with reinforcement
learning I mean you'll just keep
exploring right and then when you hit
the goal you declare success and then
you just do these trials so in fact
zillions of papers were written on that
and the what I disliked about those
papers was that they were always solving
the problem in the context of one
environment which is uh right you're
you're exploring one environment and now
you can go to different goals
chair uh you know uh sofa table Etc so
that doesn't seem so good okay that's
one answer let's think of uh is there a
way of converting this to a uh
supervised learning problem or an
imitation learning
problem
H so you find the trajectories so how
can we find the trajectories we can use
the classical techniques so there is
some
environment we have a map of that
environment because this is in a
simulator in the
simulator what we did was we scanned in
some houses or apartments or restaurants
or whatever so we've scann in those
environment so we have the 3D map so in
that environment we can always find
Optimal paths from any point a to any
point
B so this is these are optimal paths so
now we have
essentially uh the perfect form of
supervision uh given a certain uh
Target uh since I I can find the optimal
trajectories I have
this Oracle this uh which knows what's
the what's the advice to give you go
left go right whatever at any location
the Oracle can give the agent that
advice so therefore that's the
supervision for the agent and so what is
the agent going to do the agent get some
visual input the visual input is uh is
shown by this picture and then uh and it
has some gold chair and uh and then uh
it's a it's a supervis learning problem
because at a particular location you say
go left or go right or go
forward and you train the network right
and and then how would we generalize
well if I have 10 homes I can train the
system on all those 10 homes and this
system will figure
out what are more plausible ways to get
to the bathroom for example in a
restaurant
right do you
agree okay so people did that so this is
the line okay let's see if there are any
subtleties here okay so one approach
would be when you go you just learn you
I I you just have access to the current
image and you are going to take a step
as uh determined by this
policy so uh do do you see any possible
problem with that idea
huh so so it's as static in in the in
what sense the environment is static so
so yeah so there is an issue with like
moving obstacles like people but there
is another problem which is what if you
if you uh uh sometimes there are
alternative
possibilities right and what happens is
you try one possibility and you don't
get to the goal
okay next now you do you go around and
then you are back at the same
point and what will you do you will do
exactly the same thing
again right you will uh I mean so in in
a in a maze you're trying to escape a
maze you're at a certain point and you
make a you you go in a certain way you
always go left at that point because the
visual picture is the same at that point
and you will just keep repeating that
mistake repeatedly so therefore a purely
reactive
policy will will it does not do a clever
job of backtracking so it's always going
to screw up in the setting right you see
that okay so now let's think of what's a
possible fix for
that
yeah yeah so now you need memory right
so you can have memory in different ways
one way of having memory is memory of
your past
actions okay and presumably the network
can figure out while training that uh
don't do the same thing
twice the other way of having memory is
to have memory of the space so therefore
either it can be episodic memory memory
of your past
actions or it can be memory of the
space okay what does the memory of the
space sound like it's starting to sound
like a
map okay so the map idea
reappears but this is a smarter version
of the map idea right why is it a
smarter version because you don't go
around building the complete map you
just build the map of the areas that you
have explored and you keep a record of
it and you use it but you do not have to
start from uh like you it's not a blank
slate thing you you so you can do it in
two ways one is that you can use some
lstm or Gru or Transformers or whatever
to record your history the other
approaches you uh you build a spatial
map uh let's
see and and there are papers like I I I
don't think I'll uh give you I mean you
don't need to read references for this
it's pretty intuitive
okay
okay now uh this this whole game which
uh I mean so this in fact happened there
was a series of papers which were all
about navigation formulated as a
reinforcement learning problem or uh
imitation learning problem but but they
were in this style of uh being reactive
system so the term we use is reactive
reactive means that it's just using the
current information and acting on it it
has no memory either of your past
actions or of the
space and uh and this idea by the way uh
goes back ages uh so so uh people in
psychology were studying reinforcement
learning for rats and mazes so the usual
set up or okay in one place the r get
some water in another place it gets some
electric shock or whatever and it's
being trained to to go in particular
directions and and this is like this is
called beh the behaviorist Paradigm and
it was very popular in Psychology
particularly in American psychology in
the 20s and 30s and and so on and then
this person comes along whose name is
Edward Tolman who actually was a
professor at berlay in the psychology
department and there is a if you if you
go up on Hurst you see there is this
huge construction going on that's where
the the Gateway building is going to be
but the building which was formerly
there was called Tolman Hall and that
Tolman Hall is after Professor Tolman
who is like a psychology Professor
Berkeley so tolman's contribution was he
he did lots of experiments on rats and
so on you can actually find his his
lecture he gave his lecture at Berkeley
in 1948 and he said we have done these
experiments on rats in Berkeley and and
in other places as well and what is
finding was that rats are actually quite
smart so if they go through some
roundabout way and then but they can
find short short cuts so if you feel
that if you if your theory was that it's
all
reactive right uh then you you would not
get this efficiency which you get from
building a map because once you build a
map then you can find the shortest path
so if the rat has in
its brain built a map of the environment
then the rat can find shortcuts and I'm
not going to go into details of this
experiment uh you can uh but Tolman
showed quite conclusively that that rats
must have something like maps in their
brain because they couldn't find
shortcuts even though they never
actually traveled on that shortest path
they traveled in some weird way but they
built some kind of a mental
representation and this is quite
interesting this line of work Tolman was
a psychologist he had not figured out
where it was in the brain but over time
there was a lot of research in this in
neuroscience and uh the hippocampus was
the site where people uh said the maps
are and then more fine grain work was
done and anyway there were people who
got the the Nobel Prize for those
findings on uh maps in the in the
brain okay so maps maps exist maps are
there in the the brains of mice and
presumably men okay and uh okay so I'm
not getting through the going to go the
details of this finding okay so now now
I'll I'll take you through a couple of
papers where the uh so this paper uh is
from it was published in science
robotics last year I think and this
paper has a study of comparing these
different
techniques okay so there are different
techniques we can uh use now for uh for
uh finding a path to a goal where a goal
could be a geometric goal a goal could
be a semantic goal okay so this could be
a a goal could be so this is an example
of a semantic goal good go find a
plant right and uh and then there's some
strategy which I'll get
into right and we did this experiment in
that Airbnb St you rent an Airbnb put
down the robot uh then it has to uh it
does all this stuff and then it has
success when it has found the
goal
okay uh now uh these are all examples of
of uh various random
airbnbs where the robot is going around
looking for various
goals okay so uh so now let me uh so we
had what six homes three uh three
different approaches six goal object
categories I'll show you later um a
later paper which did this more
thoroughly but from this we we got some
interesting
findings uh uh let's discuss uh metrics
benchmarks so when you have a strategy
for finding a
goal right so the goal is you put the
robot down and you it goes to it's been
told find a potted
plant and uh and then you you want to
evaluate how well it
does so I want you to brainstorm a
little bit about how to evaluate an
approach for navigating to to particular
objects you you can let the robot run
and then if it manages to find it uh you
can say success so it's one or zero if
it finds a plant then you say now you're
not going to do this in practice right
you're going to have some timeout so
you'll say okay if it finds it in 200
seconds then I then it's a success and
if it is not in 200 seconds then it's a
failure okay so that's a reasonable I
mean that's that's a good idea so this
is this just binary success or
failure okay can you be smarter than
this yeah um You can compare the like
geodesic shortest distance cut and then
if the robot succeeds you compare how
long a distance
was right so this is uh the so so we can
consider normalized path length so so
because there might be you can't just
consider the the path length because
different uh because different uh uh
different targets may have different
path lengths so what you do is you first
you find the optimal path what is called
the geodesic
path and then you find out how much time
how long is the path taken by by the
robot and you take the ratio and that
ratio is always going to be greater than
or equal to one right so we take the
inverse of that
right so the inverse of that will always
be between 0 to one so that's a measure
of the efficiency if it's if it finds
always finds the optimal
path then you it gets a one if it finds
a path which is double the length then
its score is
0.5 okay we do one practical
modification to this idea which is uh
that I'm not going to wait forever so
I'll have some time out consider like
200 seconds or whatever and that if it
doesn't find it in 200 seconds then we
declare it to be a failure so at that
point it's a it's the trial is so so
what should be the the score then it
should be zero so so we this criterian
is called success weighted path length
SPL so SPL in the in the navigation
Community this is just uh this is the
lingo SP okay so SP uh if your robot is
doing very well it's it will be one if
it's always failing to find the target
it is going to be zero and it's going to
be in between so this is the way we will
compare now we can compare
algorithms I mean this is not I mean you
train it in whichever way you like but
after that we will compare
spls does that seem reasonable
okay okay and then we compared three
different
methods okay
so let's uh uh and uh so one is the
classical approach so what's a classical
approach you first build a map then you
do uh uh then there's no there's no
learning involved so if I say go go to a
chair uh uh what it's going to do is
it's going to just wander about until it
hits a chair right so that's the
classical approach okay there is end to
end learning so what's the end to end
learning way which is uh essentially uh
that's kind of obvious I I I told you
the approach right the end to end
learning is that you have you are in a
simulator in the simulator you have
Apartments of a type similar to what
you're going to encounter in the real
world and then you uh and then you train
it with in this RL or imitation learning
way and we did this uh the parameters
are there that's end to end
learning okay and then there was this
third
approach called modular
learning okay and modular learning
is that we uh we are going to build a
map okay so the modules are one is map
building so we take the idea of building
a map from classical robotics but the
map is not you don't do the slam thing
of going around everywhere to build a
map you just build a partial map based
on the area that you are uh that you
encounter it's my analogy for this is uh
when I first came to
Berkeley which was 40 years ago I did
not go around everywhere on campus to
build up my map right I go to certain
places and now I have a map of those
parts of this this campus and that's it
I always even now I have only an
incomplete map of this campus but it is
rich in the areas which
I which I go to I know Soda Hall well I
know Cory Hall well I know
saaja I know BWW but I do not know every
corner of every pixel of this campus
right okay so these are three approaches
and uh let me let me check your like you
now we have experimental findings and uh
those will come so I'm going to do a
little mystery game here of these
approaches which do you think does the
best best second best and third first
second third okay what's your guess so
let's take a poll so how many people
think that the classical approach is the
best will turn out to be the
best okay one vote for that how many
people think that end to end learning
will turn out to be the
best okay two how many people think that
the modular approach will turn out okay
so we got the majority word here okay so
yeah in this case the majority is right
uh and now uh now we'll do the so so the
module approach turns out to be the best
but what's the second
best so what is the second best approach
is it end to end or is it
classical so now let's take a poll so
now I'm asking you about the second how
many people think
classical how many people think end to
end okay again the majority is right I
mean classical wins classical is second
best okay and end to end is actually a
disaster okay in fact I mean and I say
this because uh I mean everybody is
still doing end to end right so so okay
so uh so let's just explain what the
specifics are here and and but but why
end to end is bad is interesting okay so
so that's the learn the lesson to we
learned here so this is your canonical
way you will build up a end to end
approach right you you have some uh you
have some
uh what did it okay so this no what is
what is this I can't have hidden this
guy I need to move this out
okay so uh so this is this is the end to
endend okay sorry
let's so you're looking at the image and
then uh in the modular approach what
you're doing is uh you're building this
map okay map which is partial and then
you you have a goal uh directed uh goal
oriented semantic policy so the so you
did some learning what you did learning
the map building there is no
learning the learning is on what's a
promising place to go that's the part
which you do while
learning okay and we trained in at this
time there were a number of these
simulators which had a number of scanned
in environment so that's what we used
and here are the
results success rate okay in
simulation were like this
so uh basically they're about the same
right okay now the success rate in the
real
world okay so the end to end learning
was an absolute
disaster okay and uh so so note that the
classical is is quite so in with
classical there isn't so so you should
always do a sanity check when you here
these papers so the classical approach B
there's no learning right so what it
gets in simulation and what it gets in
the real world should be about the same
and indeed that is true right uh modular
learning somehow it turned out to be
even slightly better in the real world
and why that is the case maybe the
distribution of environments in the
simulator was harder it could be end to
end learning why was it so bad in the
real
world so think about it and then I'll
give you the
answer it it turns out to be a disaster
mainly because the perception part did
not transfer so the perception part what
all you has is the RGB experience in the
simulator and that experience I mean
while fair amount it's not doesn't match
the experience
of I mean I mean there's a sufficient
difference between the the RGB looks in
the simulator versus in the real
world and so so the perception part
essentially lands up thinging okay and
this is found many times I mean this is
not this is not unique to this
navigation example there are other
settings in robotics where you'll find
the same thing that the RGB part uh gets
overfitted in the simulator and then it
doesn't work so well and uh uh anyway
there are some examples so these
examples show what the SPL was and these
These are so this is a case where uh
where a modular did very well uh end to
end was okay and classical was terrible
and probably the classical did poorly
because its exploration strategy doesn't
benefit from
learning okay uh and uh
okay and then we we did more experiments
but I I've given you the let's see if
you can find some oh yeah so this is uh
uh this maybe this terminology is worth
noting semantic exploration versus
Frontier exploration so there is
something you should know uh the
semantic exploration is that when I'm
looking for suppose I'm looking for a
TV in a someone's house I have a sense
of where I'm more likely to find the TV
right Frontier exploration means that
there is you just uh go to whatever is
the next unexplored region from your map
so there is no no benefit of learning
there so uh so essentially you get the
benefit of that right the goal is to go
to the bed and the SPL is .90 which is
very very good uh with semantic
exploration and with Frontier
exploration it's not directed by kind of
knowledge of where beds are likely to be
found so n to end fails to transfer and
uh and these are all failures of the end
turn uh yeah okay I think
I so so there is a domain Gap uh
basically the the perception it's a
perception where uh so so my uh what's
the lesson to take from this I mean okay
this is just one one paper one exper set
of experiments the lesson that I take
for this is that in robotics you uh
particularly for with respect to
perception particularly with respect to
Vision training in a simulator doesn't
give you enough data to make a really
good Vision system Vision systems if you
train them with real world collection of
images and video there there is enough
diversity to to train really good models
and then you can use them in a simulator
so train in the real for the vision
system and then use it in a simulator
it'll work fine but the other way around
doesn't work so well whether this is
true forever and ever who knows but this
is certainly the the case now so that's
a lesson I would take now let me uh let
me uh let me pause here let me do a stop
share
and uh I'm going to now H go to uh
another talk about a different paper
which is more which is the
fancier ways of doing
it let's close this okay let me just
check this
out
[Music]
okay so
okay so let me check if we are
good okay so this is a a more uh more
recent paper which uh uh let me start
with what it was what it is trying to do
it this is again the same Airbnb
experiment but just done at a much
bigger scale okay so now we used this a
spot robot but I mean we're not using
the spot in any sophisticated way it's
got a low-level stack which uh which
takes care of moving around and avoiding
obstacles so but what it's going to be
done is what's going to be done is that
it's going to be given various targets
like go to the plant go to the go to the
TV etc
etc these are all
examples okay so this is the the setup
so what the the go goal is uh so you can
see the observation from the uh
observation and the semantic map right
you're seeing that so the map is being
built up
partially the uh and it has a goal and
the goal is indicated let me let me roll
this
back so it goes a bit slower so uh do
you see the goal so the goal here is
obviously the kitchen sink and the goal
can be specified in multiple uh in
different possible ways let me pause it
uh we we consider three ways of
specifying a goal one way of specifying
a goal is you just give a picture okay
so then when you find something close
enough then it declares success another
way of specifying a goal is semantic
categories so a semantic category can be
a chair a desk a bed or
whatever okay or the third way to
specify a goal could be language so you
have a natural language phrase and the
natural language phrase can be
complicated it can be uh you know the
the red teddy bear on the green table
right you can do all of that right okay
now the strategy that we followed here I
mean so this is the the next okay wait
wait I don't want to go
there uh the the strategy we followed
here was uh had one so based on the prev
previous experiment we already knew that
we like the modular approach so we were
going to use a pre-trained vision system
not a vision system that had been train
end to end what we were going to do was
we were going to build a map because
that's a good way to avoid uh visiting
the same place twice it captures the
information in a compact way but in
addition it wasn't going to be just a
classical geometric map it was going to
have a record of the semantic so as you
go around the world you say oh here
there is a refrigerator so in the map
you make a note there's a refrigerator
or here there is a TV and you make a
note of this so you're going around the
environment you're building the map but
in addition you're
recording uh uh these
categories chair table Etc and of course
there can be more than one chair so in
which case you need to have a counter
running saying chair one chair 2 chair
three Etc
okay so fairly straightforward and uh
and then uh uh where is the other
cleverness here the cleverness has to be
uh what's uh and this has to be achieved
by training and simulation uh what's a
what's a place you should go if you
think you're looking for a chair what's
the place you should go if you're
looking for a kitchen knife and that you
train in simulation right but it's a
modular approach with some training and
simulation for the s semantic
exploration aspect the map building is
done without that's like just generic
map building there's no learning
involved there the vision system is a
deep neural network but it has been
trained Elsewhere on huge huge amounts
of
data okay so now let's uh let's just
play this
out so uh observation so this is what
the robot sees there's a goal it'll keep
going and what at the bottom what you
see is what it recording as the objects
it
sees right so you see all these objects
it sees it's then it's declared success
it found the kitchen sink now it's been
told go to the red cap on the brown
leather chair
okay but the uh the the nice thing is
whatever it sees on its way it keeps
recording that so therefore it's
learning over time it's becoming over
its lifetime as it explores the the home
even while it's doing it for task a it's
going to benefit it on task D so it's
quot uh lifetime learning
right yeah so we actually have some
experiments that for the same Target
after it's gone through the house a
little bit the SPL is better than it
would have been in the beginning
so okay so this is the goat problem okay
so this is the goat
problem so now with full
noise so I think in this demo it has to
pick up some objects and put it into
okay so so so the story is uh uh
cleaning up your house that's the
supposed okay so what was the goal
multimodal reach any object specified in
any way wait what happened here okay so
there I thought there
should uh okay wait something is wrong
with this slide anyway oh yeah I just
didn't wait long enough it could be an
image it could be language it could be a
category and then it has this lifelong
learning aspect which is how we are as
humans we never go around first building
a map we just do what we need but as we
go along we have acquired more and more
of the map of the environment so my in
my own home I know it much better than I
know in some stranger
home okay goat system architecture okay
so this is what we did we had uh okay
sensor POS
reading okay so the perception system is
basically relying on the power of
computer vision Community to have built
good models for each of these so there
is a segmentation system and uh depth
estimation geometry all of this is just
offthe shelf computer vision systems not
no end to end training
here so this is adequate for building a
semantic map and it is also adequate for
recording all these
instances right object instance memory
so you have a memory of what I saw at
various locations and this is a sensible
thing right because uh every day when I
go like for example when I go home I
know okay here there is a Starbucks here
there is a bank here is a grocery store
so our maps are not just pure geometric
Maps we also have associations of
particular locations and landmarks so it
seems reasonable that you build that
in it's a semantic
map okay and then there's a global
policy and uh okay so these are just
different ways of specifying language
goals image goals category goals you
feed that as input in some form and then
and then you it tells you where to go
but you keep building your map so you
may land up uh you may land up making a
wrong judgment you may go go left
whereas the target is actually to the
right so you'll eventually move around
but as your map becomes complete you
will know that this was a unproductive
path because this is happening in in the
training process as
well okay system architecture I think I
did perception
system
uh okay The Bu blocks here let it just
roll
out now uh this used depth I think it
could be done without depth but depth
made life easier depth was uh but the
this should it should not really need
depth because the depth information is
already
there and
uh okay
okay there's a top to map I think at
this point i' object I think I've really
gone through all the concepts here
semantic map with
Associated let me just
uh okay you you've seen all
this main ideas are build a semantic map
record instances that are seen and I
think I can end here
uh by just saying we we did this and it
worked and it really worked okay and I
will end my lecture here